<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The strangling and death of the Great Turke, and his two sonnes VVith the strange preservation and deliverance of his Vncle Mustapha from perishing in prison, with hunger and thirst, the young emperour now three dayes before having so commanded. A wonderfull story, and the like never heard of in our moderne times, and yet all to manifest the glory and providence of God, in the preservation of Christendome in these troublesome times. Printed this fifteenth of Iuly.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08162</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.62</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S122197</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857349</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857349</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23071</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08162)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23071)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 998:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The strangling and death of the Great Turke, and his two sonnes VVith the strange preservation and deliverance of his Vncle Mustapha from perishing in prison, with hunger and thirst, the young emperour now three dayes before having so commanded. A wonderfull story, and the like never heard of in our moderne times, and yet all to manifest the glory and providence of God, in the preservation of Christendome in these troublesome times. Printed this fifteenth of Iuly.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 17, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. D[awson] for Nicholas Bourne and Thomas Archer, and are to be sold at their shops at the Exchange, and in Popes-head Pallace,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 18883.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 18883 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Cropped at head, affecting pagination and some text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mustafa --  I, --  Sultan of the Turks, 1591-1639.</term>
               <term>Osman --  II, --  Sultan of the Turks, 1603-1622.</term>
               <term>Turkey --  History --  1453-1683 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:23071:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23071:1"/>
            <p>THE STRANGLING AND DEATH OF THE GREAT <hi>TVRKE,</hi> AND HIS TWO SONNES.</p>
            <p>VVITH THE STRANGE Preſervation and Deliverance of his Vncle MVSTAPHA from <hi>periſhing in Priſon, with hunger and</hi> thirſt, the young Emperour <hi>not three dayes before ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo commanded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A WONDERFVLL STORY, and the like never heard of in our <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>derne times, and yet all to manifeſt</hi> the Glory and Providence of <hi>God, in the Preſervation of Chriſtendome</hi> in theſe troubleſome Times.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed this fifteenth of Iuly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I.D.</hi> for <hi>Nicholas Bourne</hi> and <hi>Thomas Archer,</hi> and are to be ſold at their ſhops at the <hi>Exchange,</hi> and in <hi>Popes-head Pallace.</hi> 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:23071:2"/>
            <q>
               <l>HAud ſic magni conditor orbis,</l>
               <l>Huic ex alto cuncta tuenti,</l>
               <l>Nulla terrae mole reſiſtunt,</l>
               <l>Non nox atris nubibus obſtat,</l>
               <l>Quae ſint, quae fuerint, Veniuntque,</l>
               <l>Vno mentis cernit in ictu,</l>
               <l>Quem, quia reſpicit omnia ſolus,</l>
               <l>Verum poſſis dicere ſolem.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Boetius Metro. 3. Lib. 5.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:23071:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The Printer to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am very loath to trouble you with a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, yet at this time you muſt pardon me; for it is for Gods cauſe, to exemplifie his glory &amp; providence, that hath put an hook in the noſtrils of <hi>Leviathan,</hi> and kept him from devouring poore <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who yet are in Armes to devoure one another: that hath throwne a ſtone from Heaven to ſtrike the golden Image to powder, which was ſtretching it ſelfe, to overlooke and overtopp the <hi>Provinces</hi> of <hi>Europe;</hi> that hath put an Axe to the great tree, and felld it at a blow, which was beginning to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread the earth, and be a ſhaddow for the beaſts of the field. What, all <hi>Chriſtendome</hi> almoſt in Armes, and yet the <hi>Turke</hi> not to take the advantage, but to be pulld ſhort by the hand of God, and throwne backward into a graue? Where are your dreaming <hi>Gazettes,</hi> and <hi>Coranto's</hi> now, that talkt of ſuch formidable preparation, and ſo many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand in an Army? Where is the threatning of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and terrifying the <hi>Coſſacks</hi> with ſo many thouſand <hi>Tartarians?</hi> Where is their comming into <hi>Hungary,</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin a new Warre there? What all huſht and quiet? Why, then thine be the honour O God, and all power, and maieſtie, and goodneſſe be attributed vnto thee? For thou haſt taken pitty vpon our afflictions, and wilt ſet vpright thine owne cauſe, when the children of <hi>Edom</hi> and inhabitants of <hi>Babylon,</hi> cry downe with the walls of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and inſult with clapping
<pb facs="tcp:23071:3"/> their hands, to ſee the enemies of the Goſpell thriue in their outragiouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>This then is all I would ſay vnto you by the way of Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, to giue God the prayſe, that the great <hi>Turke</hi> is dead ſo opportunely, whereby there is hope, that <hi>Europe</hi> ſhall be preſerved from their inuaſion, and thoſe affrightings. And the ſame God, that hath compaſsionated the generall diſtreſſes of <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> take pittie likewiſe on the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular paſsions of <hi>Princes,</hi> that they rage not in their reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, nor runne too violently forward in their race of bloud and deſtruction; but admit of peace and pacification to the eternall memory of their vertues, and worthineſſe.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:23071:3"/>
            <head>THE STRANGLING AND DEATH, OF THE GREAT TVRKE, A STRANGE STORY.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough I neede not ſpeake a word of former Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours of <hi>Turkey,</hi> or their actions, or their liues, or their <hi>Alcharon,</hi> from whence the ſpeciall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions on their Governerment are, firſt, to erect ſome Famous <hi>Monument</hi> toward the exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Religion. Secondly, and performe ſome memorable enterpriſe for the enlarging their <hi>Empire:</hi> yet muſt I name <hi>Mahomet</hi> the third, to keepe my ſelfe cloſer to the Story, that you may know the ſeverall paſſages in the ſame. This <hi>Mahomet</hi> left two Sonnes behind him, <hi>Achmet</hi> and <hi>Muſtapha; Achmet</hi> at 15. yeeres old was choſen Emperor, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſome 15. yeeres longer, or thereabouts and although by reaſon of the peace betweene the Emperour <hi>Rodulphus</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> &amp; him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as alſo the contract betweene the <hi>Pelomans</hi> &amp; himſelfe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thoſe <hi>Antiqua foedera</hi> were renewed, he did little worthy of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, concerning Heroijck enterpriſes, and military exploites: yet he had the Fortune to keepe correſponde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy with his <hi>Basſhawes,</hi> and <hi>Ianizaries,</hi> and tooke a courſe by enlarging their entertainement, and other ſeverall donatiues, to enlarge their heartes, and good li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king towards him: ſo that he had very ſeldome mutinies, or inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, becauſe the <hi>Viceer</hi> of the Army drew them ſtill into the field in the Summer, and the <hi>Viceer</hi> of the City, afforded them their Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient liberty in the Winter: but at laſt there was a rebellion by the <hi>Serivano</hi> of <hi>Aſia,</hi> whom ſome confound with the name of <hi>Basſhaw</hi> of <hi>Alleppo,</hi> which was fortunately, and wiſely prevented: and in the ende of his Raigne the controverſies of the Princes of <hi>Molda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via,</hi> over wrought the <hi>Polacks</hi> to commiſerate the cauſe &amp; wrought a miſchiefe, which was not ended without vnſpeakeable trouble: For the diſtaſtings beginning in <hi>Achmets</hi> time, could never admit of reconciliation: till <hi>Achmets</hi> Sonne came in perſon with terror, and threatnings into the fieldes of <hi>Bogdonia.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:23071:4"/>
            <p>Well? <hi>Achmet</hi> dies, leaving 2. young Sonnes behind him, <hi>Oſman</hi> and another: yet ſome will preſume to ſay, that being not aboue 34 yeeres old, he had many Children, and 300 Wiues or Concubines: but before he dyed, to make all ſure, he reſolues to ſtrangle his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> and according to cuſtome will leaue no Competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in ſuch an <hi>Empire.</hi> For which purpoſe a Guard of <hi>Capagies</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend at the Iron gates of the <hi>Seralio,</hi> and the <hi>Mutes</hi> are placed in a roome accordingly. Now you muſt conſider, that though they haue many wayes to enlarge their cruelties, and diſpatch offenders, yet none is ſo affrighting, as the preſenting of theſe Officers, for they never come along without death in their company, and ghaſtlines in their lookes. Sometimes an offender is carried from the <hi>Seralio,</hi> by the Officers of their <hi>Tapinaco,</hi> ſuch as we ſay M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. of the Ordna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, over the Sea, &amp; in the midway a great ſtone is tyed about his neck, and he is caſt into the bottome, and then according to his greatnes, a greater Cannon is ſhot off, vnleſſe the Emperour ſend a counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; er he be from the water: ſometimes an offender is beheaded: ſometimes throwne off a rocke: ſometimes ſet vpon by the <hi>Ianiza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> &amp; cut in peeces, as the <hi>Haga</hi> or Captaine is limited, yet in theſe caſes as the Emperors fury is leniated, they many times eſcape: but when the <hi>Mutes</hi> come in place, all are diſplaced, againſt whom their Commiſſion is enlarged. Thus is <hi>Muſtapha</hi> to be diſpatched, but ſee how the ſtronger arme puts out the ſtrong men? the ſame night <hi>Achmet</hi> had a <hi>dreame</hi> or fearefull <hi>viſion,</hi> which ſome of the <hi>Deruices</hi> would needes preſume to rumor abroad, in this manner; that hee thought as he was entring into the 7. Towers, the princely priſon of his Predeceſſors, his brother kneeled downe before him, and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, Oh when ſhal we leaue this horrible cuſtome of ſhedding in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent blood? looke among all the Heathens, and ſee, how quickly they loathed and caſt away that crying Sin of ſacrificing of humane fleſh? but in ſteede of replying he drew his Semiter to ſtrike off his head, had not one as hee conceited held it faſt, that hee could not ſtrike; whereupon he demanded angerly, what art thou? I am the good <hi>Genius</hi> of <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> and will not ſuffer him to periſh, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore leaue: and very ſhortly ſhall ſtrange things happen in the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.</hi> Little thought the great Turke, to haue found a greater Greatneſſe in his ſleepe, but ſuch was the power of God, or as
<pb facs="tcp:23071:4"/> the Turkes conceited the fortune of <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> that his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Achmate</hi> contrary to all expectation the next morning after his Dreame, ſent for him into the roome of <hi>State,</hi> where he lay on as ſtately a Pallet, with all his <hi>Viceroys</hi> and <hi>Baſhaws</hi> groueling on the ground, and the principall <hi>Mufty</hi> knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling before him reading on a booke. It ſhould ſeeme that glad tydings came firſt to the Citie; For hee was taken out of the priſon with great reſpect, and obſeruation: hee was admitted to his Gally with high ceremonies, and yet ſolemne countenances: hee was accompanied on the Sea with thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of boates, and tenne thouſand of weeping eyes: hee landed at the Emperours one <hi>Caska</hi> with great reſpect and modeſt ſtilneſſe: hee walked through the Garden of <hi>Cipres</hi> trees, and at laſt came to an iron gate, where his owne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany left him, except two <hi>Baſhawes,</hi> who led him by the armes: the gate opens and he muſt through a gard of <hi>Cupo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies,</hi> they bend to the ground, and yet looke cheerefully: till at laſt the Prince ſpake as cheerefully to the <hi>Baſhawes,</hi> ſaying What need all this quoile and ceremonies to a dying man? or tormenting of my ſoule, when I goe to the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my body? in all extremities there is a curteſie in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatch, and when a man muſt dye, Oh let him dye at once, and not be more tortured with the feare and circumſtances, then with the thing it ſelfe: they durſt not reply; but brought him into the roome, where the <hi>Mutes</hi> ſtood: whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence did no more appall him then the reſt, but that hee ſaw the cruelty confirmed, and their very ſight was worſe, then an vnreuerſable iudgement: but when hee perceiued no violent hands laid vpon him, and that he muſt yet goe further, he was the more aſtoniſhed, and the more vexed to endure ſuch a procraſtination.</p>
            <p>At laſt he came where the Emperour lay ſicke on his Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, before whom his proſtitution was as the ordinary ſlaues: but contrary to all expectation he bad him riſe, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded certaine Perſian Carpets to be ſpread, &amp; rich Cuſhions to be laid; on which, according to their manner, he ſate croſſe legg'd by him, and when the <hi>Mufty</hi> had raiſed the Emperor
<pb facs="tcp:23071:5"/> vp a little, with a faint voyce, he thus diſcouered an vnlookt for louing heart.</p>
            <p>Brother (ſaid hee) I am taught by ſtory, and the ſtory of <hi>Galba</hi> among the Romanes, to chuſe a Succeſſor for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, and not an heire in my family. This made him looke vpon <hi>Piſo,</hi> as worthy to be an Emperour, becauſe hee had experience of his vertues, and not vpon his kindred, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee was vnacquainted with their ſtrength to beare ſo great a burthen: I cannot compare our greatneſſe with the Romanes, but I am ſure wee are too great for children, or fooles: I haue faire iſſue of my owne, but ſo weake armes cannot ſway the Scepter of our <hi>Othoman</hi> family, and to leaue them vnder <hi>Tutelage,</hi> Who is there worthy to aduiſe ſuch Princes, or what account can ſlaues make of the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when their owne vices ſhall ouerflow their bankes without reſtraint, and the enuie of others look vpon them ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with diſobedience, then obſeruation? therefore to auoid all tumultuous occaſions, and to make thee beleeue, thou art the charge of our <hi>Prophet Mahomet:</hi> in ſteed of death-like preſents it ſelfe in ſteed of a priſon: this is thy Pallace, and whereas thou camſt in groueling, thou ſhalt goe out trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing: the decree of heauen will haue it ſo, and a voyce from heauen commands it ſo; only this I muſt conclude, that as I haue remembred thee, thou wilt not forget me and mine, let not cuſtome ouermaſter vertue, nor the iealouſie in Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty be an enemy to thy pitty: but let young <hi>Oſman</hi> liue as I haue determined, thou ſhalt not dye: yea, the wonder is the greater, that of a captiue I haue made thee an Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and in ſteed of the terrors of affliction, brought thee out to the rauiſhings of <hi>Maieſtie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He had no ſooner done, but he began to faint, and ſo read them all a leſſon of mortality by opening a booke, wherein they ſaw death writ in Capitall letters, and himſelfe ſinking paſt recouery, which made them recouer new Spirits, and preſently bring his brother out into the <hi>Sophia,</hi> where the principall <hi>Mufty</hi> proclaimed <hi>Muſtapha</hi> Emperour, intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Ianizaries the charge of <hi>Achmate,</hi> to the diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
<pb facs="tcp:23071:5"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> larges, which equalling the bounty of other Princes, ouerſway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nicer exceptions, and ſo with great acclamations they rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the Election, and cryed out, liue and raigne great <hi>Muſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha.</hi> The next worke was the ſolemnity of <hi>Achmets</hi> Funerals, for whom a ſumptuous monument, and <hi>Chappell</hi> was erected, not inferiour to any of his Aunceſtors: then were Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners appointed to ouer-looke the <hi>Seralios,</hi> and ſequeſter ſuch women, as had beene carnally knowne of <hi>Achmet</hi> to their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed Pallaces, and accuſtomed manner of magnificence, and expences. Preſently followed the ſetling of the <hi>Baſhawes</hi> in their authority, in their ſeuerall Prouinces, and ouer-looking the Citie Officers with confirmation of ſuch, as were worthy. Laſt of all, his Armies and Nauies were muſtred, not that hee pretended any warre, but becauſe he would commit no Solle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſme in gouernment, or giue the Souldiers occaſion to ſuſpect, that he knew not, how to maintaine his greatneſſe: Thus is <hi>Muſtapha</hi> Emperour, and they had two yeeres triall of his diſpoſition, whereby they found him harmleſſe, and rather ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the Epithites of quiet Princes, then tranſcending Enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mions of great and ſtirring Spirits.</p>
            <p>But oh the condition of man, and inſtability of terreſtiall bleſſings! Prince <hi>Muſtopha</hi> was ſcarce warme in this throne of Soueraignty, and ſetting forward in the rare of imperiouſnes, before <hi>Scander</hi> and <hi>Mehemet Baſhaw</hi> takes the young <hi>Oſman</hi> out of the <hi>Seralio,</hi> and preſents him to the Ianizaries, a comely, ſweet young youth of nine or ten yeeres old, demanding with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, if ſuch an heire of the <hi>Othomon</hi> family were to be reiected without cauſe, or why they ſhould bring an harmleſſe Prince (as they reputed <hi>Muſtapha</hi>) into the danger of vſurpation, and differing no further from a Traytor, but that it was not impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, as for <hi>Achmats</hi> Will? Empires are not ſo tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and what could they tell, but priuate men for their owne ends had wrought vpon his weaknes, making a diſeaſed tongue ſpeak that, which a healthfull heart, and perfect ſence would not conſent to: For it was not probable, that a Father would diſinherit his children for any brother in the world: Beſides, there was no triall, or cauſe either of inſufficiencie, or diſability,
<pb facs="tcp:23071:6"/> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> not beleeue it. La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of all, for any thing they ſaw, <hi>Muſtapha</hi> himſelfe was not ſtirring or ſtrong enough to play the Steeres man in ſuch an high built ſhip, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the Seas were tempeſtuous, and many dangerous ſhores and rockes were to be paſſed by.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſpeeches to the turbulent Ianizaries, were like fewell to fire, and the preſence of the louely youth, made them amazed at their inconſtancie: ſo that by way of penitencie and ſatisfaction, they quickly altered the acclamation of liue <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtapha</hi> into the cries of, God ſaue young <hi>Oſman,</hi> and ſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further diſputing, hee was aduanced into the Throne, and brought into the <hi>Seralio,</hi> when <hi>Muſtapha</hi> leaſt thought of the alteration. But now there is no remedy, he muſt needs be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and ſent priſoner once againe into the ſeauen Towers; his friends more confounded to be ſo affronted, then amazed at the alteration: yet ſuſpecting the worſt, they abandoned the Pallace, and thinking it pollicy to ſhift for themſelues, had the leſſe honeſty to neglect their Emperour: but the truth is, they ſaw manifeſt ſignes of a rebellion, and the conſpiracie was too great and too ſtrong for them to reſiſt, which made them giue way to the violence, leaſt they ſhould haue beene caried head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Now doth <hi>Oſman</hi> begin his <hi>Phaetons</hi> flouriſh, and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the courſe of pleaſures with his youth, ſpending foure or fiue yeeres in wantonneſſe and iollity, while his <hi>Baſhawes</hi> ſpent the time in couetouſneſſe and ambitious ouer-ruling o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: yet not without carefull ouer-looking the Ianizaries, and prouident preuenting their diſcontents, and turbulent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: but all doth helpe; for they ouer accuſtomed to actiue imployment, and liuing vpon the ſpoile of forraigne Nations, as much as the Emperours entertainement, cried out to the warre, and when anſwere was made, that the Perſians had contracted a new league, and the Emperours of <hi>Germanies</hi> old couenants were not yet determined or ended, They preſently replyed, the indignities which the Ruſſians had offered to their neighbours the Tartarians, were not to be endured, and they need goe no further, then the piracies of the black Sea, and the iniuries of the Coſſacks and Polonians:
<pb facs="tcp:23071:6"/> Nay, why ſhould they not march to the expugnation of <hi>Locpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> and the foraging of the Countries of <hi>Moldania</hi> and <hi>Bogdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> and ſo forward to teach <hi>Poland</hi> a better leſſon, then to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe the <hi>Othoman</hi> Family and mightineſſe.</p>
            <p>The Baſhawes knew, there was no replying, nor now the fire was kindled no other quenching it, then letting it conſume to cinders, wherupon they preſently anſwered, they were glad that the Souldiers were ſo memorable of the glory of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and ſo ready to imploy themſelues for the dignity of the Nation, and therefore they would not by any meanes hinder them, or the cauſe: But they ſhould find the Emperor as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to ſatisfie their demaunds, as they were willing to augment his Greatnes: ſo that if they would giue way vnto time for the preparing of all things fit for the Army, and the ſending for the Tartarians to accompany them in the iourney, the Emperour ſhould goe in perſon into the Field, and <hi>Poland</hi> ſoone finde, what it was to exaſperate ſuch a Maieſty.</p>
            <p>Whereupon ſome will haue it, that there were Letters of defiance preſently ſent againſt <hi>Sigiſmond,</hi> and the Warre pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claymed by ſound of Trumpet to affright all <hi>Europe:</hi> In what manner the Turke proceeded, I will not now diſpute, ſure I am that the King of <hi>Pole</hi> made all Chriſtian Princes acquainted with the threatnings, and implored their aſſiſtance for the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: He ſent vnto the Emperour to hearken to a Peace, if it were poſſible, and correſpondent with his Honour, that he might ſpare his Forces rather againſt the generall Enemy of Chriſtendome, then the particuler reuenges of one another: Oh bleſſed be the feet of thoſe, that bring the glad tidings of Peace, and happy is that Princely diſpoſition, that would auoyde the effuſion of Chriſtian Blood: hee ſent vnto his Holines to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the cauſe of the Church, and the affrightings of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, ſo that now was the time to aſſiſt him with men and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and if euer <hi>Poland</hi> were reputed the Bulwarke of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, and to be maintained accordingly, it was at this inſtant to be looked vpon with the eyes of pitty and commiſeration. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>00000. Turkes and Tartars were in readineſſe to ouer-runne the Country, and deuoure the Inhabitants: He ſent into <hi>France</hi> by way of interceſſion to ſpare his hand fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> taking ſuch fearefull reuenges on his owne people, &amp; to ſpare him but thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:23071:7"/> men, watch the wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> confirme, and the wrath of a Prince bring to deſtruction: he ſent into <hi>England</hi> with intimation of the terror, which ſo many barbarous Nations &amp; people vnited, muſt needs afflict one Countrey withall, and his well deliuered diſcourſe made ſuch impreſſion on his Maieſties Princely hart, that he had a preſent ſupply both of men &amp; money: In a word, whether did he not ſend to ſet forward the enterpriſe? and what did he not doe befitting the goodnes of a King, &amp; the greatnes of a Generall, and heroyick Captaine? his Army was ſoone rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and his Coſſaches prepared: by the end of Iuly he was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camped in the fields of <hi>Bogdonia,</hi> and within 8. dayes entrenched with 20. pieces of Ordnance mounted: but the Coſſacks quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by themſelues, &amp; after their accuſtomed manner lying be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene two Riuers, were the more emboldened to make their daily excurſions vpon the Tartars: For hauing a bridge in the reare of their Campe, with which the Turkes were vnacquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, they quickly tranſported their men, and as quickly endem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified their enemies.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>Gran Signeur</hi> was made acquainted with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes of theſe <hi>Polonians,</hi> and vnderſtood they were already encamu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, and expected his comming, he was too young to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend any feare, &amp; not olde enough to lay the blame of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tardance where it was: therfore they made the more haſt, when he vnderſtood the occaſion, and ſo according to former prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the eſtabliſhment of diuers Gouernments, the ordering the Prouinces, the ſetling the great Citty, the muſtring his Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes, the guarding of his Caſtles, and the watching of the blacke Sea: the Tartars vnited themſelues to his Army, &amp; both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther made a body of 200000. which with all magnificent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration he preſented in the ſame Fields, and within ſight of the <hi>Polonians,</hi> where he pitched his Imperiall Tent, and ſetled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with vnparaleld Maieſty: the high Prieſts and Doctors of Law attended him, the two great Baſhawes accompanied him, the throng of Ianizaries waited vpon him, and the fry of Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars brought the Cariages vp apace.</p>
            <p>When all thinges were ſetled, the Tartars after their accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med manner with great clamours and outcryes, and with as great multitudes gaue vpon the Polonians, and thought to haue
<pb facs="tcp:23071:7"/> made but one battaile &amp; day of tryall of the buſines, but when they came to paſſe ouer Riuers, and aſſaile Trenches, when they heard the thunders of 20 Pieces of Ordnance, and felt the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe and damage: when they were encountred with 10000. well armed Horſe, and driuen backe with the fury of couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hearts: they knew not what to ſay, and leſſe to doe; nay, though the Ianizaries came as a ſecond vnto them, and brought many field Pieces to anſwer the diſcurteſie of their Camp Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, yet by reaſon they had not the diſcipline of Gabions, they were ſubiect to the greater deſtruction, and the Souldier wanting Armor found themſelues too weake for the Coſſacks: whereupon they retreated, &amp; were altogether appawled to be ſo diſapointed, which whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Scander Baſhaw</hi> perceiued, he tooke an opportunity of exprobrating their audatiouſnes, and chiding their oſtentation, whereas now they could performe nothing, which he did as ſome report to this or the like purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Now, you that are ſo powerfull in inſolency and tumults, and were ſo forward to the War, that we muſt either take the Field to ſpend your humors, and ſatisfie your impatience, or be taken by you, &amp; ſuffer the indignity of your outrages, what ſay you now to the Warre? what can you doe to theſe men? nay, what will you doe for the Emperors Honor, and your own reputation? well, ſeeing you ſee by experience, that the times are changed, and the diſcipline of Warre muſt take you out o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leſſons of fury, leaue your fooliſh finding fault with your friends: and ſpend your courages vpon your enemies? there is now no retiring by Mutinies, but ſetting forward vpon aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, you muſt either force theſe Trenches, or be enforced to indure a ſlaughter: But I will now anſwer for you, what is paſt is remedileſſe, we come to Fight, and I know, you are reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute to play the men, therefore follow me, and I will leade you the way to death or Glory: wherupon without any reply, they came forward with 50000. and vnder the ſecurity of a rowling Trench gaue a braue Camizado on the <hi>Polonian</hi> Campe, with many pieces of Ordnance, which they mounted vpon prety bankes, as the Pyoners caſt vp the earth before them.</p>
            <p>But as they were in this forwardnes rhe Coſſackes came ſo violently vpon the vnarmed <hi>Tartars,</hi> that they were ſubiect to
<pb facs="tcp:23071:8"/> a great ſlaughter, ſo that both they and the Ianizaries were glad to retire with loſſe, and the young Emperor vnacquainted with the Warre, was yet acquainted with Oathes and Curſes, to chide both himſelfe and Fortune. At laſt the Baſhawes ſeeing no remedy and finding ſo great obſtacles of their attempts, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected the preſeruation of the <hi>Emperors</hi> perſon; but it may be to ſecure their owne liues, &amp; ſo entrenched themſelues, being (as they ſaid) the firſt time that euer ſo great an Army of <hi>Turkes</hi> was encloſed within walles, by which occaſion, neceſſity com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peld them to confeſſe, they had new worke in hand, and that there was nothing ſo eaſie, as to cry to the warre, but nothing ſo difficult as to returne with Victory.</p>
            <p>In this manner they lay all the Summer looking vpon one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other with reuengefull eyes, and taking the aduantage of ſo many Sallies, that the Turke loſt at leaſt in ſeuerall Skirmiſhes 50000. men: For many times they met about the ſeeking of Victuall, and there fought it out: many times they encountred in forraging, and getting prouiſion for their Horſes: many times their courages were ſo exaſperated, that with equall incoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and appointed Sallies they returned home againe, finding the iſſue nothing but ſlaughter and bloud, and many times they determined to deceiue one another by taking the Riuers and paſſing the Foords, which ended not without deſtruction, and periſhing of whole Companies. As for ſet Battails, or one dayes tryall by equall agreement of both parties, it neuer came to ſo formidable a buſines, or remarkable aduenture: and therefore I can but wonder at the ſhameleſſe reports of ſtrange men, and weake Certificates by <hi>Corantes</hi> from Foraine parts, eſpecially to haue them Printed, to talke of ſo many Thouſands ſlaine, the Prince kill'd, <hi>Sigiſmond</hi> defeated, and the whole Army put to flight, when yet as I ſaid, there was neuer any ſuch matter, nor any ſet Battaile fought.</p>
            <p>Yet although the <hi>Polonians</hi> had rather the better, then the Turkes, they did not runne away ſo faſt with proſperity, but they were ſubiect to many inconueniences, and they ſawe plainely the warres were no May-games: For they endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi rend="sub">r</hi>ed both Hunger and Colde, ſlacknes of payment, and <hi rend="sub">t</hi>heir entertainment came many times ſhort: The Noble</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:23071:8"/>
            <p>The noble Generall died in the Campe, the Prince lay ſicke of a Feuer, their horſe miſcarried, and other lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble effects taught them extraordinary patience, which made them attend good conditions of peace, and when they found they might be entertained, they were not ſcrupulous or thought it any deſparagement to propoſe the ſame.</p>
            <p>When the Baſhawes were thus diſappointed (eſpecially <hi>Mehemet Baſhaw</hi>) who was euer an enemy to the <hi>Moldauian</hi> buſines, and that he ſaw the yong Emperour euery way diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented, but eſpecially with himſelfe, as blaming his owne vnhappineſſe, that hee ſhould in the firſt triall of his manhood be ſo vnfortunate, as to open the doore of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian apprehenſion; that the <hi>Othoman</hi> fame was now at the higheſt, and the Turkiſh Empire ſubiect to diminution: hee went another way to worke, and perſwaded the yong Prince to make tryall of another time, and peace for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: nay he did talke of another countrey, to which when the Turke angerly replyed, he would die firſt, hee enforced the argument that it ſhould be to his honour, and the <hi>Polack</hi> ſhould ſeeke it with great mediation.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid, the yong Emperour ſhed teares, and was more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of his diſceputation among his ſouldiers, then glad of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pacification of the preſent troubles; yet neceſſitie had no law, and he was in the end compelled to the propoſed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. But how? By a polliticke contriuing the buſines, and ſecret workings of more nimble ſpirits: for preſently a Prieſt of <hi>Moldauia</hi> was ſet on worke to go among the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians,</hi> and by way of generall complaint againſt the outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious effects of warre, to enlarge the happineſſe of peace, and inferre what a bleſſing it were to procure the ſame: whereupon hee was brought to the yong Prince of <hi>Poland,</hi> and commanders of the Army, with whom hee at laſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed ſo well, and ſo farre, that they ſent a ſolemne Embaſſie to the great Turke, as he lay entrenched in the fields, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate a peace, and deſire the renouation of the <hi>antiqua pucta,</hi> which had been euer betweene the two nations. The Turke had learnd his leſſon ſo well, that hee ſeemed to make the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:23071:9"/> matter ſtrange and of great humiliation, if he ſhould conſent thereunto, and rather a curteſie granted then a neceſſitie im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and ſo deferred them a while, till at laſt (as if he had bin ouer-wrought by the interceſſion and mediation of his Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhawes) he was contented to capitulate the matter, and after many meetings, and a great deale of conference, articles were drawne, and confirmed with a kinde of ſolemnity, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed by ſound of trumpet in both the campes.</p>
            <p>But ſee the condition of men, and the inconueniences that great Emperours are ſubiect vnto? for all the <hi>Ianizaries</hi> themſelues neither durſt, nor could maintaine the warre any longer, and were indeed affronted with an ouer-maſtring power, and an ouer-ruling diſcipline of warre: yet they ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther complained of the Emperor, as being vnfortunate, then their owne cowardice, as being ouer-mated, and ſo brake vp the campe with a kinde of murmuring and repining. The great Turke tooke eaſie iourneys toward <hi>Andrinopolis,</hi> where he diſcharged the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and ſent moſt of his <hi>Ianizaries</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand to <hi>Conſtantinople. Sigiſmond</hi> king of <hi>Poland</hi> raiſed his army, and rewarding the <hi>Coſſacks,</hi> diſmiſſed them home againe into their country: he went in perſon to <hi>Leopolis,</hi> from whence (by this time <hi>Oſman</hi> was come to the great cittie) he ſent a ſolemne Embaſſador to be there a Leiger, as it had bin in former times.</p>
            <p>By Chriſtmas <hi>Oſman</hi> comes home, and had the accuſtomed acclamations of the people, with all the ceremonies of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, whereupon he goes in great pompe to the <hi>Sophia,</hi> and had the vſefull guard of his Court <hi>Ianizaries</hi> to attend him: but within ſhort ſpace many fearefull accidents appalled them all, and ſuch a miſchiefe followed, as they could not example by any preſident. Firſt, they were aſtoniſhed at a blazing Comet, about which many men did raue in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation. Secondly, they were afrighted at a great fire hapning amongſt the <hi>Iewes,</hi> which they preſaged ominous to the gouernment. Thirdly, a ſore earthquake made their hearts quake for feare: but this is ſo vſuall in thoſe parts by reaſon of the aſcending vp the hills, and many Cauerns vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:23071:9"/> ground, that they needed not haue made it, or taken it for any ſigne of diſpleaſure. Fourthly, the Sea ſwelling extraordinarily, and the winde from the Southweſt driuing the billowes into the corner of the harbour, made ſuch a noyſe and formidable ſound, as catching the tackles of the ſhips and gallies in his whiſtling, that they were affraid euen of common accidents.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, and worſt of all, by reaſon of the great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of people, and reſort of ſtrangers, ſuch a famine happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the city, and dearth in the countrey, that euery one complained, and though it was remedileſſe by the pollicy of man, yet was the fault layed vpon Superiours, and the Emperour himſelfe did not eſcape ſcandall and calumnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>For while the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iceers</hi> and principall Officers endeuoured the common good, and ſtudied the Weale publike, which could not be done, but by diſcharging the Citie of multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of Inhabitants; all was interpreted to be done for their priuate wealth, and ambitious ouer-ruling of others: but when it came to the diſcharging of many <hi>Ianizaries</hi> and ſouldiers out of the Citie, to liue as it were in garriſon in the Countrey, and that the Emperour was ſlacke in their Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, and former allowances out of his Treaſurie; they ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med beyond meaſure, and threatened the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iceers</hi> and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhawes</hi> to haue a better account of the Buſineſſe; crying out, they would not be quiet, till they were imployed in one Seruice, or other. To this the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iceer</hi> replyed, that hee wondered at their baſeneſſe and audaciouſneſſe, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing fayled in all their Enterpriſes, they durſt yet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of any accident, more then their owne cowardize. As for the ſatisfying of wilfull men, they would not vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the Lawes of Nations, or infringe the contracted Peace with other Kingdomes, to appeaſe the mutinies of turbulent ſpirits, who, if they might haue their owne demaunds, knew not what to demaund. As for your ſelues, what would you haue? you know the treaſure is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:23071:10"/> &amp; the dearth is ſo great, that we haue not ſufficient to buy vs bread: and for your murmuring and repinings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Maieſtie of the Prince, as if he alone were branded with misfortune, or borne vnder ſome diſaſtrous conſtella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; how can this be, that with the ſame hands whereof you boaſt to vphold the Empire, you will preſumptuouſly pull it in peeces; but I ſee the reaſon, this is for lacke of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline to make you know your ſelues, and ſo I cannot reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you better then vnto ſtinking weedes and nettles, which cruſhed hard, looſe their force, and cannot hurt at all; but gently handled, will ſting and endamage one.</p>
            <p>Till this they were not much enraged, but now no flames could exaeſtuate more then fury and rauings: for they dared to condemne the Viceeres, and cryed out on their childiſh and vnfortunate Emperour, that hauing neither ſufficient wit, nor courage to gouerne the State, muſt be ouer-ruled by ſuch, as made pollicie, couetouſneſſe; and ambition, the ſupportation of their greatneſſe, and the commanding voice to do what they liſt, without controule: yea ſuch was the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractary diſobedienee of them at this time, that many offred to lay violent hands both on himſelfe and his ſeruants, and had not the <hi>Haga</hi> or their Captaine come in to their pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, they had queſtionleſſe begun a warre of miſchiefe, and inſolent trouble.</p>
            <p>Well, they are quieted all this time; the ſuſpition of fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vprores and miſchiefes made the whole citty to ſtand vpon their guard, and euery Baſhaw ſtrengthned himſelfe with as many friends as he could, and the Viceer for ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Emperor aſſembled the <hi>Chauſes, Cappogies, Spahies,</hi> and <hi>Ianizaries</hi> of the Court to guard the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> and watch the paſſages. Now you muſt conſider that there hath been e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer enmity and emulation between theſe <hi>Ianizaries</hi> of the pallace and <hi>Ianizaries</hi> at large, whereupon when theſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, that they were appointed for oppoſition, and ſaw plainly there was a deuiſe to ſingle the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out, that ſo they might be brought in queſtion for their mutinies: they reſolued with <hi>Heroſtratus,</hi> that burnt the temple of <hi>Diana,</hi> to performe ſome
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:23071:10"/> nefarious and notorious outrage, to be remembred to poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, or be regiſtred for an exorbitant action: and ſo in mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes paſt beleefe, they ſet vpon the Emperours <hi>Seraglio,</hi> broke open the yron Gates, diſſipated the Guards, ſeized on the Women, tooke as many <hi>Baſhawes</hi> as they could: but the chiefeſt reaſon why they offered this outrage, is as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sultan Oſman</hi> hauing taken out of the Treaſurie of ſeuen Towers a good quantitie of Gold, and being therewith paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ouer into <hi>Aſia,</hi> with reſolution to goe vnto <hi>Mecca:</hi> the great <hi>Mufti,</hi> his father in law, hauing laboured with all the greateſt of the Court, whom it pleaſed not at all, that their Emperour being ſo young, ſhould make ſo farre and long a Voyage; not being able to remoue him from his reſolution, as hee deſired, did in pollicy ſpread a rumour abroad, that the Emperour had taken ſo many Millions of Gold away with him, purpoſing therewith to make new Warres againſt his Enemies, notwithſtanding the ſmall ſatisfaction hee had giuen in the late Warres againſt <hi>Poland.</hi> Which comming to the vnderſtanding of the <hi>Spahi</hi> and <hi>Ianizaries,</hi> they riſe, and in a furie ranne vnto the Tower wherein <hi>Sultan Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtapha</hi> was impriſoned, and taking him thereout, ſaluted him Emperour, who was lawfully elected by the father of <hi>Oſman.</hi> This comming to the knowledge of the young Emperour, hee ſent his <hi>Grand <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſier</hi> and the <hi>Aga</hi> of his <hi>Ianizaries,</hi> to appeaſe the ſame, who were preſently ſlaine by the ſouldiers in their furie. By which accident, the young Emperour, to remedie this diſorder, being forced to come himſelfe in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, was inſtantly made priſoner, and brought to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his vnckle <hi>Muſtapha;</hi> who hauing framed Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt him, cauſed him to be carryed priſoner to the ſame Tower where hee himſelfe had beene priſoner, and the night following to be ſtrangled, with two of his ſonnes but lately borne: Which was moſt inhumanely comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> his owne vnckle; who for the more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie, to keepe the Empire from another vſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion, cauſed it to be effected.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:23071:11"/>
            <p>It is alſo written, that although hee condiſcended to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer into their hands all the chiefe men they required, which were the principalleſt of the <hi>Ottomans</hi> Court, who afterward were all ſlaine with the ſword; though hee proffered them great gifts, yea to encreaſe their ſtipends, and other prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: all could not auayle, to aſſwage the anger of the ſouldiers.</p>
            <p>It is further reported, that the Emperour had giuen in charge to the Keeper of the Tower, that hee ſhould ſuffer <hi>Muſtapha</hi> to die of hunger, to auoid thoſe diſgraces and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents which ſince are befallen him: and it ſeemeth hee had alreadie ſuſtained ſome want of foode; for ſo ſoone as hee came to be ſet at libertie by the people, hee preſently cryed out for Water, ſaying, hee was ready to die of thirſt, and that if hee had not come out of priſon when hee did, hee preſently had yeelded vp his life, being (as hee ſaid) won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully preſerued by his God <hi>Mahomet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the young Emperour <hi>Oſman</hi> was brought to his preſence, hee kneeled on his knees, and craued pardon of him for his life, as heretofore <hi>Ottoman</hi> had done the like to him: but <hi>Muſtapha</hi> anſwered, ſaying, that fauour I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued commeth from heauen, and not from your hand.</p>
            <p>Hee afterwards cauſed the Grand <hi>Mufti,</hi> the great Turkes vnckle, to be put to death, who had formerly bereaued him of ſo great an Empire, and made him a <hi>Maſul,</hi> which is as much to ſay, as a man depoſed from his Office. Hee placed in the roome of the dead Viſier, <hi>Daut Paſcias,</hi> a man of great wiſedome, and one that had demeaned himſelfe well in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of greateſt importance.</p>
            <p>It is alſo ſaid, that the death of the young Emperour is very ill taken by the ſouldiers, for they deſired the death of none of them, but that they might be reconciled, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne them as their naturall Lords and Princes, as they beſt could agree; and the rather, for that by reaſon of the death of the aforeſaid <hi>Oſman,</hi> the whole race of the <hi>Ottomans</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed, if the two children are put to death, as is reported, for that Sultan <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> now Emperour, is held vnable for generation.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:23071:11"/>
            <p>Others report, that Sultan <hi>Oſman</hi> was not as yet gone ouer into <hi>Aſia,</hi> but was vpon going, and that the <hi>Mufti</hi> and other his adherents not being able to remoue him from his reſolution, did vſe this but as a deuice to diuert him, caſting this rumour among the people, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Spahi</hi> and the <hi>Iani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaries,</hi> as is aforeſaid, which happened to his ruine, and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination and ending of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire.</p>
            <p>To come to a concluſion; neuer was ſo violent an act ſo ſuddenly performed, nor ſo quickly repented: For the <hi>Iani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaries</hi> ſtood amazed at their owne villanie, &amp; by night there was not a man ſeene, that durſt iuſtifie their treaſons; for they fled for the preſent, no man knew whither, and thoſe which remained, were afraid to ſtand for the glory of the Houſe of <hi>Oſman,</hi> but they would liue and die in the obedience of a worthy Emperor.</p>
            <p>But how this vprore ceaſed, or tumult was appeaſed: what offendors bee taken, or how puniſhed: what <hi>Baſhawes</hi> bee ſlaine, or from whence others are admitted: by what meanes the Doctors of the Law came together againe, or whether they eſcaped; if you long to know, I long as much to informe you: which (if I may doe) I will doe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the next Certificate that comes.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
